【苏醒的亚当】
我曾经到过一个美丽的幻境
I had once the beautiful fatherland.
那里树木参天
The oak tree grew so high there.
鸦默雀静
Violets nodded softly.
那是一个梦
It was a dream.
亲抚过我的脸庞 用德国 用德语呢喃
It kissed me in German and spoke in German.
简直无法相信那听起来是多么美妙
You would hardly believe how good it sounded,
那句话 Ich liebe dich 我爱你
the words, ich liebe dich, I love you.
那是一个美梦
It was a dream.
[特拉维夫(以色列港市) 1961] [Ruth Edelson 民宿]  ***
亚当
Adam.
亚当 到时间了
Adam, it's time.
对不起 宝贝儿 在外面等等
Oh, my landlady Ruth Edelson.
我有点事想问你
Let me ask you something.
我今天早上是不是
Am I still handsome this morning?
还是一如既往的帅气
Tell the truth now, come on.
你当然很帅 亚当
Of course you are, Adam.
的确到时间了
I don't think there's any time for the-
早餐时间
for the breakfast.
你知道我从未问过你
You know, I have never asked you, my darling,
亲爱的 你芳龄几何
how old are you?
老实说你心里有我
Forgive me, you are the witch.
对么
You are the hexer.
让我告诉你我到底有多帅
You have swindled time.
亚当 别这样
Adam, please.
在昨天晚上第一觉之后 亲爱的
After you fell asleep last night, darling,
我就在想
I lay there.
我的女神
I was thinking,
皮肤有着不同寻常的嫩滑
"My God, this woman's skin is unnaturally smooth."
就像POTRSLAND
It is like porcelain.
事实上我可以看到我自己的想法
In fact, I can see my reflection in it.
[唱歌]
[singing]
没人藏到那儿吧
Now, what are you hiding under there?
亲爱的 让我看看
Darling, show me.
- 来 看一下  - 别 亚当
- Show me, show me.   - Adam.
过来 偷看一下
Come here, just a little peek.
嗯 看看
A bruise?
[门打开]
[door swings open]
对不起 亚当 相信我
I'm sorry, Adam, believe me.
原谅我 亚当
Forgive me, Adam.
早上好 亚当
Morning, Adam.
跟我们走吧
All set to go.
好 我还有一些话要说
Ja, do not forget this Olivetti please.
快点 伙计 快点
We won't, pal, come on.
原谅我 亚当
Forgive me, Adam.
我不该通知他们
I shouldn't have called them.
原谅我吧
Please forgive me.
没事儿 Ruth
It's all right, Ruth.
没事儿 就像
Oh, you taste like...
肥皂一样
soap.
你为什么做那件事 亚当
So why'd you do it, Adam?
做 那件事
Do it?
你为什么认为我干了
What is it you think that I did?
你知道 你那些魔术把戏
You know, that old magic trick
你把女人切割 为最终让她们尖叫
where you separate a woman's spinal column from her skull.
像小宝贝一样啜泣
Choking his landlady.
噢 这真是 实在是太荒谬了
Oh, this is- that's ridiculous.
是啊 他并没打算伤害她
Nah, he didn't mean to hurt her.
只是让我们把他再次带回家
Just wanted us to bring him home again.
就像亚当这样
Right, Adam?
是的 喔 喔
Yeah, woof, woof.
我感到很亲切 我再一次被带回到
And so I was once again returned
这个沙漠中的家
to my home in the desert,
Seizling研究所
The Seizling Institute,
由美国慈善家Rebecca Seizling建立
founded by American philanthropist Rebecca Seizling
他在Nathan Gross医生的指导下建立了这个研究所
as a center under the direction of Dr. Nathan Gross
为药物的创新
for innovative therapy
也作为纳粹集中营幸存者们的家
and as a home for the survivors of the Nazi camps.
好
Muhammad.
[讲外语]
[speaking foreign language]
你看到没
Do you see that?
快点
Come on.
他们在等着了
Big guy's waiting.
是的，我说我的爱
oh I say I say my love
噢 亚当
Adam.
又见到你了
[speaking foreign language]
哦，是的，又见面了
oh yes I say my love
噢 Akson
Oh, that's a big hug.
对不起
He's back.
他身板硬着呢
I am so happy to see you too.
是的 是的 亲爱的
Yes, still sweeping.
我会在你的地板上
Am I tracking-I don't want to track sand on your-
追踪你的
on your floor.
嗨 你好 Rebecca
And heil to Rebecca.
我最亲爱的朋友们
All my best friends.
这是什么
What's this?
噢 交通运输系统
Oh, transport.
他回家了么  - 天啊 什么事
Have they all gone insane? Wel...
200美金
Two hundred bucks.
亚当 我藏了有几个月
Adam, been hiding them for months.
我们有10或者22
You've got to tell me what to do.
AT&T Brown先生 在纽约
AT&T, Mr. Blum, New York Stock Exchange.
早午餐的时候给我
Here, give it to me.
我会给你两倍
I will double it for you in- in no time.
- 亚当  - 在
- Adam.   - Ja?
哥伦布是犹太人吗
Columbus was Jew?
是的 是的 夫人
Yes, yes, Mrs. Lipowitz.
哥伦布当然是犹太人
Columbus was definitely a Jew
啊 还是意大利人
but also an Italian, so as a matter of fact,
我不信任意大利人和音乐人
I would not trust an Italian, and neither should you.
是的 那是真的 就像法国人
Ja, it's true, they're an enlightened bunch.
但他们得检查一下
But they licked the jackboot,
不能期望每个人都对此有帮助
and now they expect everyone to forgive and forget.
[婴儿啼哭]
[baby crying]
[女人咳嗽]
[woman coughing]
- 我的火车  - 是的
- My train.   - Ja.
你
You.
我会告诉你 你知道这里是Seizling
Really, Arthur, you know that Mrs. Seizling strictly forbade
这里有吃有住 像教堂
any form of locomotive combustion at the Institute.
我的火车
My train.
我告诉你了 你在这里很安全
Arthur- [speaks foreign language]
你知道我在说什么
You know what I'm talking about.
我们得以幸存
Fellow survivors, it's so good
所以能够回到这个研究所真好
to be back here at the Institute,
尽管不是作为同住者 不是作为研究员
though not as inmate, not as guinea pig.
不 这次我是肩负着
No, this time, I am on the mission
揭穿Seizling研究所里的
to expose the lunacy
医务人员的任务来的
of the medical staff here at the Seizling Institute,
有人认为过失行为应该得到弥补
the negligence, Dr. Shapiro,
而她的教授
and the impotence
Nathan Gross的不耐烦
of Herr Professor Nathan Gross, et al.
他在说谎
He's lying.
Arthur是谁养大的
Authorized by whom?
（绕口令）
[speaking foreign language]
我 我 我 了解
然后她来了
And here she comes.
就像你听到她的脚步声
I could hear her methodical footfalls
和你的心跳
and irregular heartbeat.
那是Gina Grey
Nurse Gina Grey,
走下坡路的一个伙伴
a pearl in a dunghill,
很有原则的人
a book of rules,
还有那漂亮的屁股
and with that classy ass.
[喇叭吹响]
[trumpet bugling]
Arthur 请别吹了
Arthur, please stop that.
不
No.
不 不
亚当
Adam.
请跟我到Gross医生的
Would you come with me?
办公室打个招呼 好吗
Dr. Gross wants to say hello.
不 不
No. No.
Brown先生 请把这些药片吞了 好吗
Would you please swallow those pills, Mr. Blum?
我也要
[speaks foreign language]
现在还没到时间
Hmm, not now.
你瘦了些 亚当
You've lost some weight, Adam.
噢 是的 我一直都在想你 我的Gina
Oh, ja, I was-I was pining for you, my child.
夜不能寐 你知道的
The nights have been the worst, you know.
嗯
Hmm.
我听过你的谎话了
I've heard about your nights.
而且你不是故意伤害她的
But I'm sure you didn't mean to hurt your landlady.
请进 亚当
Come in, Adam.
如果
Oh, come here, Gina.
你喜欢这样
Let me smell something.
噢 就像那样
Oh, ja, just like I remember.
啊 摸我
Touch me.
摸我
进来吧 宝贝
Come in already.
是啊 你喜欢那么做 不是吗
Yes, you love doing that, don't you, Adam?
嗯 噢 是的 迅速占有她
Uh, oh, ja, the- the sharp transition.
你有空吗
Here one moment...
没有 亚当
You know, Adam-
下一个是谁
Gone the next.
嗯 我想不出
What I can't figure out,
为什么我们要帮你
why haven't we been able to help you?
你是个聪明人
You're a brilliant man.
你有过天赋
You've been called a genius.
被命名为亚当・斯坦的王国
Name: Adam Stein, next of kin: none whatsoever,
我是其中一环
number on my arm:
我也把生命融入其中
sieben, sechs, drei, vier, fuenf.
女人 也是其中一环
Gross, file it away and let me go.
好的 你拥着无数女人入怀
And yet, you see, for all your knowledge,
然而研究所
your sixth, seventh sense, here you are
在不到24小时之前
back at the Institute after trying to kill a woman
试着杀死一个女人
less than 24 hours ago.
那是说谎
This is a lie.
噢 不 那是说谎
No, this is a lie.
- 噢 不 啊 是的  - 那是说谎
- Yes.  - No, that's a lie.
你知道那个名字 Ruth Edelson
A woman named Ruth Edelson.
你是在开玩笑 对吗 开玩笑
And you, Gross, you are- you're a joke.
你想要告诉我为什么吗
Ah, do you want to tell me why?
是的 回想当时 据说是值得相信的
Ja, back there, it was absurd to believe...
许多事情
in anything.
有人相信
In the sun we did not believe.
你看到美丽的地方 相信许多事
And yet you, here of all places, you believe in miracles.
你不仅是信任他们 你依靠他们
You not only believe in them; you depend on them.
没有敌对与谎言 这就是天国
This is not only hilarious; this is chutzpah.
- 亚当  - 呃
- Adam.   - Ja?
在这个研究所里只有一个人
There's only one person in this institute
你可以和他协作
who can work miracles.
和他合作
They're circus tricks.
我可以一天之内教他们把戏
I could teach them to you in a day.
听着
Listen, Grossie.
我曾经是你们的明星
See, I've been the-the star of your-
只有失败
your medical experiments,
和痛苦
and you have failed miserably.
所以不要跟我说什么奇迹
So don't you dare talk to me about some miracles.
那让我的事业失败了
Now, of course, my job is to fail.
你让人向上爬
I am the sick dying clown.
和我没关系
Fine, this is my business.
但是你所谓的帮助我
But what have you done to help me,
是为了帮助其他人
to help any of us?
是 你是对的
No, you're right.
我从内心深处感到抱歉
And I'm sorry from the bottom of my heart.
[讲外语]
[speaks foreign language]
我打赌 只要你知道
As long as you know.
让我们看看怎么回事
Now let's just see what's going on
你可爱的私人的
with your lovely personal affairs.
不 不 等等 等等
Oh, now, wait a minute.
情人
Please.
亚当 住手
Adam, stop.
啊 这是你的日子 不是吗
It has not been your day, has it, Doctor?
所以我可以轻松解决
Some milk of magnesia.
解决问题 考虑病人
That would solve the problem.
这实在太恐怖了 我们不是圣人
Constipation, it's a horrible thing, but don't strain.
够了
Cut it out.
你不想忍受那样的痛苦
You don't have to suffer that way.
但是你 有更具有建设性的方法
If only you'd use your gift a little more constructively.
如果我可以想要 我就可以做到
Oh, I could if I wanted to.
但你知道 我不想
But, you know, I-I do not.
这里依然还留着些东西
[speaks foreign language]
不 我会成为一个你的奇迹 而曾经不是
No, I am going to be your miracle that never was.
是的 我以前就听说过这些了 亚当
And we've heard all this before, Adam.
出去 休息下吧
Go on and get some rest.
出去 起来
Go, already. Get out of here.
这该死的东西是哪来的
Where the hell is all this coming from?
你知道
And no pulse.
曾经有过饥荒之年
Maybe in a hundred years,
你知道 谁帮助亚当・斯坦度过的
we'll know how to help the Adam Steins of this world.
嘿 亚当
Adam.
- 退后 Rachel  - 亚当
- Step back, Rachel.   - Adam.
离他远点
Get away from him.
Rachel
Rachel.
- 是时候了 亚当  - 靠边
- Is it time, Adam?   - Step away from him.
Rachel
Rachel.
噢 亚当
Oh, thank God.
上帝保佑你
The birth pang of the Messiah.
我就知道
I knew it.
太好了
They've begun.
噢 看呐
Oy vey.
你能回来真好 亚当
It's good to have you back, Adam.
[柏林 1926]
这是您的披萨
Frau Fogel, the whisky in the baby bottle, please.
我的亲爱的妻子
My wife, Gretchen.
小露丝
Little Ruthie.
谢谢你 福格尔夫人
Thank you, Frau Fogel.
啊 威士忌
Ah, malt whisky.
[干杯]
[cheers]
这不是睡前牛奶吧？
It's for the good night's sleep, ja?
好吧 谢谢
All right, please.
噢
Oh.
是的
Gretchen.
太贴心了
So sweet.
Blech
Blech.
她不喜欢
Ah, she doesn't like it.
She doesn't like it.
啊 最昂贵的一曲
The most expensive Stradivarius.
马上开始
Here we go.
[演奏忧郁的小提琴音乐]
[playing melancholy violin music]
[撕布]
[cloth tearing]
[笑声]
[laughter]
[柏林 1930]
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
让我们欢迎
meine Damen und Herren
亚当・斯坦
Adam Stein.
噢 亲爱的
My wife, Gretchen.
你太漂亮了
Oh, so beautiful.
噢 不 不 不 你不能亲
Oh, no, no, you cannot keep survival off the stage.
在舞台上不能这么做
Don't scare me like this.
亲爱的
My darling.
我需要一位元观众配合我
A volunteer.
哦 妈哈
all: Oh-ma-ha.
哈哈
Ja-ha.
噢 我喜欢这个
Everybody loves this.
不 没有观众愿意吗
No, you volunteer too often.
噢 这位先生 请 我感觉你行的
This fellow, please, may we?
啊 请
Bitte nicht.
我马上就感受到你了
Please, my eye fell on you right away, please.
感谢你的帮助 掌声鼓励
Such a good sport, give him a hand.
噢 他很害羞
He's shy.
好吧 我们以前有没有见过
All right, now, have we ever met?
我们认识吗
Do we know each other?
- 不  - 不？
- Nein. - Nein.
好的
All right.
这位年轻人 女士们先生们
This young man, ladies and gentlemen,
呃 今晚并不想来看表演
well, did not want to come to Adam's circus tonight.
他另有目的
This man had other plans.
就在这个晚上他要
This very night he intended...
结束他的生命
to take his own life.
[人群喘息]
[crowd gasps]
不 我的朋友
No, my friend, no.
别这样
Please, do not go this way.
让我来做点什么
Let me just glean just a little.
或许会有些好消息
Maybe there's some good news here.
我看看
Let me see.
是的 我们大学生
We have here, folks, a graduate of Heidelberg Universitaet.
噢 尽管显然 不是 傻学生
Oh, though, obviously no- no star pupil.
这是所谓的一劳永逸地方法
This is Zyklot 17, the animal tranquilizer.
是的 永远地摆脱痛苦
Ja, for the permanent relief of pain.
是的
Ja.
哦
Oh.
噢
[人群喘息]
[crowd gasps]
[鼓声]
[drum roll]
[掌声]
[applause]
[笑]
[laughing]
[众人笑]
[crowd laughing]
告诉她 让我一个人呆着
Tell her to leave me alone.
我已无大碍
I do not have the strength.
你听到我吩咐你做的事了吗
Do you hear what I'm asking you?
如果我想听到的话 我会听到的
I would if I wanted to.
但我不想
But I don't.
你这是在干什么
What the hell are you doing?
闭嘴 躺下 给我腾点地方
Shut up, darling, and move over.
我要疯了
You are insane.
我回忆起了那些噩梦
I am calling the night nurse.
就在这里为你服务 亚当
Right here at your service, Adam.
[柏林 1936]
我喜欢你 姑娘
欢迎来到这里
女士们 先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
我们欢迎我的女儿到台上来
we bring now to the stage my daughter,
神奇的有才华的 Ruth小姐
the amazing, the brain-bending, Miss Ruthie.
Ja, ja, ja.
[掌声]
[applause]
她很棒 不是吗
Isn't she so amazing?
你不会受伤的
You are my angel.
所以别害怕
Do not be frightened.
你什么也看不见 对吗
You cannot see anything, can you, Ruthie?
- 看不见  - 看不见
- No.   - No.
她说看不见
She says no.
噢 让我介绍下 我亲爱的妻子
She's looking askance at me, my-my darling wife.
我喜欢看到她的笑容 我的妻子
Oh, I love to get a smile out of my wife.
向我挥手
Give her a big hand.
下去那里
What's down there?
噢 我喜欢这样
Ah, I love that.
哇
Ow.
我 我下面要做的十分危险
My wife, Gretchen.
我拿起第一把刀 请安静
I pick up the first blade, so absolute silence.
看刀
Here we are.
[笑声]
[laughter]
Ruth
Ruthie, don't.
你别想在道具上动手脚
She will do anything to avoid this part.
你不喜欢这个 但还要继续
You don't like this part, but no brain bending.
这是...
That is-
[笑声]
[laughter]
[掌声]
[applause]
当你把面巾掀起来 向观众抛媚眼的时候
When you pulled up the thing and you winked at the audience
他们都疯狂了 你在跟我开玩笑
and they went crazy, you were killing me.
这就是表演
That stays in the show.
爸爸
Papa.
你是个小天才 我说
You are a little genius, I think.
爸爸 有人
Papa, there's a man.
这是你的临场发挥 还是你之前就想好了的
Was that spontaneous, or did you work it out before?
告诉我
Tell me.
- 这是你的优势  - 亚当 是他
- That's your bit.   - Adam, it's him.
Volk
Volk.
党卫队
Well, Herr Stein.
在此处表演必须是艺术学会的会员
All performers must be members of the Reichstheaterkammer.
你没有资质
You do not qualify.
（读文件）
No sense of humor at all.
告诉我
Tell me this.
呃 你们喜欢那头大黑熊吗
Did your men like that bit with the bear?
射死它
Erschiessen.
[枪声]
[gunfire]
你被逮捕了 亚当
You were warned, Adam.
我不懂政治
I am not political.
人人都爱马戏
Everyone loves the circus.
我告诉我自己
Well, I have to admit,
这里的事情很有意思
things have been less interesting around here.
看上去不可思议
It seems incredible.
昨天那个男人居然
A man who only yesterday spewed out
莫名其妙地大拇指出血了
streams of blood from his toe.
我提到过那个人
Not to mention the pancreatic tumor he sprouted in March.
他很有幽默感
And the heart attack last summer.
他以前在马戏团工作
The man has actually spat out part of a lung.
太不可思议了 听上去像是毁灭者
I mean, it's an amazing thing, the self-destruction.
亚当・斯坦不可思议的地方
The amazing thing about Adam Stein
在于不能控制他的身体
isn't his control over his body.
那么就是你的力量了 Nathan
It's his power over you, Nathan.
好吧
What?
我觉得还有其他的工作人员有牵连
And a few other staff members I could name.
放轻松 Uri
Relax, Uri.
好好吃你的饭吧
Eat your foie gras.
- 噢 亚当  - 看看谁来了
- Adam.   - Look who's here.
是 Wolfowitz 亲爱的
And, Wolfowitz, now look,
听我说 你看上去好可怕
mein Gott im Himmel, you look just awful.
只是 啊 不那么好
It's just not- not good.
啊 瑞秋 你这小子
Ah, Rachel, oh, you pumpkin.
你太美了 真的很美
Gorgeous, absolutely gorgeous.
你撑住天 免得天塌下来
And Zelda, dear, ja, you keep the sky from falling,
但是 坐下吧
but-but sit.
亚当 Shwester又做了
Adam, Schwester's been dreaming again
乱七八糟的梦
with her nonsense.
她说很灵 非常灵
She says it's soon, very soon.
她是对的 Wolfowitz
And she is right, Wolfowitz.
是的 美人 你梦到什么了
Yes, beautiful, what is it?
告诉我
Tell me.
他昨天晚上又来了
He came again last night.
嘘
Shh. - It's a secret?
天使
The Archangel.
躺在我身旁
He lay beside me and said,
他们说这次亚当真的回来了
"This time Adam has returned to lead the sufferers,
永远的回到沙漠中
"the bearers of the blue numbers, to the desert.
门永远不会为他打开
The gates of heaven will open and"-
不 当然会打开 当然会打开
No, of course- of course I will, Rachel.
那一天就不远了
That day is near, but not yet, dear.
但还没到 亲爱的
Not-not before lunch.
至少午饭之前不会
I will usher and proclaim and rescue.
我会 我应该玩救援游戏而不是马戏
Me, the clown?
你看到了
You see that?
你知道 他从病人们那里弄钱
You know he takes money from the patients?
糟透了的黑市
Invests it in the stock market.
Gross
Gross.
你...
You?
我们都是为了研究所 Slonim
For the Institute, Slonim.
我的意思是 无论他到底是个什么样的家伙
I mean, whatever else he is,
他都是一个非常有用的顾问
he's a very astute financial advisor.
Wolfowitz和Shwester在那里
You're worse than Rachel Schwester over there.
她认为他有些不正常
She thinks he'll lead them all to salvation.
亚当 我有话要跟你说
Adam, I need to talk to you.
不 等会儿再说 等会儿
No, later, later.
[嗅]
[sniffing]
怎么了
What is it?
怎么了 亚当
What is it, Adam?
怎么了
Hoof beats?
Gross
Gross.
谁让狗进来的
Who let a dog in here?
听着 谁让狗进来的
Nathan, who let a dog in here?
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
这里没有狗
There's no dog here.
我第一天来这里的时候
When I first came here,
他们就答应我 这里永远永远都不会有狗
they promised me that there would never, ever be any dogs.
你们 怎么能
How could you?
冷静点
Calm down.
[嗅]
[sniffing]
[狗叫]
[dog barks]
[狗嚎叫]
[dog howling]
Edward, how are you today?
[狗叫]
[dog barking]
[whimpering and barking]
上帝啊
My God.
[吠叫]
[barking]
[咕噜声]
[grunting]
亚当
Adam.
[咆哮]
[growls]
没事
All right.
好了 亚当 好了 亚当
Come on, Adam, come on.
好了
Okay.
是的 对
Ja, good.
对
Good.
是的
Ja.
[扬声器上讲德语的人]
[man speaking German over loudspeaker]
[Stellring 1944]
爸爸
Papa.
怀着希望
You are my angel, Ruthie.
你就会看到光明
Do not be frightened.
[狗叫]
[dogs barking]
[男人用德语喊叫]
[men shouting in German]
你
You.
亚当・斯坦
Well, Adam Stein.
全德国最滑稽的人
The funniest man in Germany,
被运到了Stellring 一个严肃的地方
delivered to Stellring, of all places.
过来 亚当
Come here, Adam.
我到这里来是计划之外的
I am Commandant Klein.
能在这里见到你 我简直无法形容我有多高兴
I can't tell you how happy I am to see you here.
你应该唱首歌
You should have seen him at the circus in Berlin.
演出你能表演的任何戏法
Any kind of animal, he could do it.
这样的一个小丑
Such a clown.
快点 亚当
Go on, Adam.
表演个戏法
Do a trick.
因为爱
Make us laugh.
出来 出来
妈妈 妈妈
Mama, Mama.
你看
Ruthie?
他们要把我带走
Where are you taking me?
妈妈
带走
不 不
No, no, no.
不 不 不 扮一只狗
Now-now do a dog for Rex here.
往右边 右边
你交了一个好朋友 亚当
You've made a friend, Adam.
你们的行为就像对好友
The smell of a Jew usually sends Rex into a frenzy.
一般犹太人会直接送去集中营 把他带到养狗的地方
Sergeant, take Herr Stein to Rex's pen.
不 亚当
No, Adam...
用四肢前进
on all fours.
这样的走路姿势太有趣了
It's funnier that way.
对 四肢着地
噢 就像那样
不 亚当
Go on, Adam...
Olivetti会得到所有的肉
or Rex will get all the meat.
那时我观察了你的事业
I followed your career, Adam.
你开始失去感情了 不是吗
You studied philosophy at Heidelberg, didn't you?
有趣的是我们没有错过
Funny we never met there.
司令官 别这样 求你了
Herr Kommandant, please.
我视情况
I'm a keen observer,
扮演国王 侍者 学生
a student of the Semitic phenomenon.
当然你不是
Of course, you're not an average specimen,
为德国庆祝的小丑
Germany's most celebrated clown.
你是个超人 亚当 可以扫除阴霾
You're a superman, Adam, practically Aryan.
所以 或许我们可以互相帮助
So maybe we can help each other.
把头低下
Head down.
不许直视我
Don't look at me.
生活还是生存
A life for a life.
这是为你好
Mine for yours.
你跟着我 逗我笑
You stay here with me, make me laugh,
让我从繁忙的公务中解脱一会儿
keep my mind off the business outside.
相信我 这绝对是美差
Believe me, it's a thankless job.
我的妻子和女儿呢
My wife and daughters.
你说什么
What's that?
大声点 亚当
Speak up, Adam.
我的妻子和女儿呢
My wife and daughters.
[笑]
[laughs]
已经在讨价还价了 亚当
Bargaining already, Adam.
这也算人之常情
The Semitic phenomenon in action,
站到我脚边这儿
right here at my feet.
但不幸的是我只是执行者
Unfortunately, I am only Untersturmfuehrer.
而不能改变规矩
I don't make the rules.
不过我们还能再讨论
But we'll see.
我们有的是时间
Yes, we have plenty of time.
克莱科斯
Rex.
过来 亚当
Go on, Adam.
很好 亚当
Wonderful, Adam.
吃
Now, eat.
给我吃
Eat.
很好吃
Schmackhaft.
[狗叫]
[dog barking]
任何有爪子的东西都别出现在我面前
Nothing with claws or paws.
不管它打扮成什么样
Seizling gave me her word.
285房间是观察室
Room 285 is in the observation ward.
禁止旁人进入
It's off-limits.
Gina告诉我
Now, Gina tells me
你们昨晚又在地板上睡了
that you slept on the floor again last night.
她说你能相信我吗
Oh, is this how you're going to break me, Gross,
养狗的女孩儿
with a dog?
不错啊
Well, nice try.
但是看看我吧
But look at me.
看到了吧 微笑着
See? I'm smiling.
不是的 亚当 你在哭
No, actually, Adam, you're crying.
这是 这是 水
It is- Ja, you momzer-water.
我刚喝了水
I had a-I had a drink of water on the way.
用眼睛喝
Through your eyes?
别这样 亚当 你会好起来的
Come on, Adam, you can do better than that.
好了 我已经做好准备
Okay, I am ready for you, Frankenstein.
接受你的实验了 现在我们开始吧
If experiments are your game, then let's play.
好好表现吧
Give me your best shot.
不过 在你杀了我之前
But before you cure me,
你一样也疯了
you will all go crazy yourselves.
285房间的门是锁的
The door to 285 is locked.
[吹口哨]
[whistling]
很高兴见你心情好转 亚当
I'm glad to see you feeling better, Adam,
不过我现在实在很忙
but we're a little busy at the moment.
[吹口哨]
[whistling]
现在不是时候
Not now.
[吹口哨]
[whistling]
亲爱的 我们能在一起哭泣
You and I, my darling, we're going to cry together,
我要品尝你的眼泪
and I'm going to drink your tears.
是的 我要这样做
Yes, I love very deeply.
这才是浪漫的极致
It is the romance supreme.
你明白吗
Do you understand, my- my dar-
规矩就是规矩 亚当
There are rules, Adam.
关心
Compassion.
同情呢
Mercy.
护士
You're the nurse.
你是怎么…
What-what happened to-
你破坏了一点小规矩 你就破坏了整个系统
You break the tiniest rule, you break the entire system.
你也是规矩的崇尚者
Do you know who is also a great believer in the rules?
嗯？
Hmm?
跟我一起犯罪吧
Kommandant Klein.
哇
Ow.
多么可怕的话啊
What a terrible thing to say.
我只是说了表达爱情的话
Ja, well, I only insult people I love.
你爱我的话
You don't love me.
就把我当成狗
You treat me like a dog.
没错
Ja, exactly.
出现在我身边的
Oh, but you're so wrong.
全是你 我控制不了我自己
With you, I lose control.
什么也无法改变
When I was strangling the landlady,
我想的都是你
who do you think I was really strangling, Gina?
你
You.
你这个混蛋
You bastard.
来吧
Do it.
像只狗一样 我的甜心
Do it like I taught you, sweetheart.
你真让我这样
No, they'll hear me.
就现在
Do it.
去吧 躺在那
Ja, down on your knees and crawl.
这是对的
That is correct.
[尖叫声]
[yelping]
这听起来还真像
Ja, but that sounds like a schnauzer.
我要猎狼犬
I want the wolfhound.
[吠声]
[barks]
[吠叫]
[barking]
噢 我喜欢
Oh, I like it.
[吠叫]
[barking]
哦，对了
Oh, that's right.
[吠叫]
[barking]
没错
Oh, that's right.
[吠叫]
[barking]
你真不是好人 亲爱的
You're despicable, darling.
用完了就给我
Just give it back when you're done.
[狗叫]
[dog barking]
你看到我吗 看得到吧 野兽 算是吧
Let me see what kind of beast has Gross brought here.
让我看看你什么样子
Let me see what you are.
来吧
Come here.
[咆哮声]
[growling]
哇！
Ow!
[呜咽]
[whimpering]
你知道你不能来这儿的 亚当
You know you can't be in here, Adam.
走吧
Come on.
过来 我们走
Come on, let's go.
坏狗
Bad dog.
你这条坏狗
坏狗
Bad dog.
让我给你带上手铐
Okay, let me see your hand.
我告诉它我会再来 它听懂了
I told it I'd be back, and it understood.
滚回去吧
Get back in there.
[呜咽]
[whimpering]
真是垃圾
The stench.
你看到它的脸了吗
Lying in his own goddamn feces.
我试图控制自己想打人的冲动
But the attendant, that flea-bitten gibbon,
但没有成功
he did not.
亚当 停下
Adam, stop.
停下
Stop it now.
[咳嗽]
[coughing]
狗娘养的
Son of a bitch.
疯子 杂种
Crazy son of a bitch.
在希特勒之前 我们还是被欧洲其他国家仇视
Before Hitler, we were hated by the rest of Europe,
除了犹太人 但我们的长久坚持
loved only by our Jews,
让他们最终了解
who somehow convinced themselves
我们两国的命运是一样的
that our two nations shared a common destiny.
就像一对信徒
A pair of pariahs,
我们本是同根生
so said your man Kafka, that demented Hebrew.
难怪这些重大事务
Sprung from the same bosom.
都是我们商讨之后
No wonder it's such messy business
决定的
vomiting you from our midst.
亚当
Adam!
下来 孩子！
Down, boy!
太过分了 无规矩不成方圆
Without rules, there is chaos.
我知道你并不感激这一切
I know you can appreciate this.
但我告诉你 就连性交也要按规矩来
Even in a circus, there are rules.
如果不做那些呢
Herr Kommandant.
我能过去吗
Those trucks outside, the Red Cross.
嘘
Shh.
你不会想跟那些人一起走吧
You don't hear Rex begging for favors, do you?
他们开始把犯人带去曼斯特夫了
They are taking prisoners to Matsdorflager.
让他们多带三个人去吧
Ask them to take three more.
那是纳粹的任务 去拯救保护平民
Rex knows his role: to serve and protect.
你知道你的任务 是来安慰我 取悦我
You know yours: to comfort and entertain.
谁知道呢
And who knows?
那个地方不一定安全
Maybe that in itself can save a life, yes?
是的 长官
Yes.
谢谢
Danke schoen.
你看 亚当
Look, Adam.
你看我给你准备了什么
Look what I found for you.
****曾经用过的
It once played in the Dresden Orchestra.
这是弦乐团的乐器
There's been some rethinking.
我们专门为你留的
We have new work for you.
[狗叫]
[dogs barking]
快点走
很好听 亚当
That's nice, Adam.
亚当・斯坦
Adam Stein?
Frau Fogel
Frau Fogel.
听着 亚当
Listen, Adam.
Ruth没死
I have news.
那边安静
Quiet over there.
她在德国境内
Ruthie's alive, inside Germany,
某个特殊地方
someplace special.
继续  亚当
Play it, Adam.
[演奏忧郁的小提琴音乐]
[playing melancholy violin music]
你哭了 亚当
You're crying, Adam.
这是
It is water.
我之前喝的水
I had some water before.
我杀了他吗
Did I kill him?
差一点
Almost.
你要更加小心 亚当
You've got to be more careful, Adam.
我们还需要你
We still need you.
谢谢
Danke schoen.
听着 亚当
Listen, Adam.
看看这个
I've had it.
我一个月前找到这个 1962年的东西
In a month's time on Purim's Eve in 1962,
其实在此之前 我就该入土为安了
Abe Wolfowitz is going to be a dead man.
什么？
What?
我已经在申请让上帝接受我
I've been sewing my own shrouds from bed sheets.
别告诉Gina
Don't tell Gina.
你不是要把我一个人留在这个疯狂的地方吧
You are not going to leave me alone in this madhouse, Abe.
我是认真的 亚当
Seriously, Adam.
我和他
Me and-and Him,
我要和他好好交流交流
we're going to have it out once and for all.
我想知道
I want to know how-
为什么他可以这么冷漠
how He could be so cruel.
要是他不下来找我 我就上去找他
And if He won't come to me, I'll go to Him,
你帮我写申请
and you'll write my eulogy.
好吧 我帮你写
Okay, I-I'll write your eulogy.
多么可爱的小孩啊 我的小Naomi
Such a beautiful child, my little Naomi.
她一点都不像我
Didn't look anything like me.
而像她的母亲
Got it all from her mother.
亚当 你把这些写下来
You write it down, Adam.
我写给谁 交给谁 上帝吗
What do I write, Wolfie, addressed to whom, God?
上帝也要去吃午饭了
God is out to lunch.
留个留言吧
He left a note, see, on your- on your arm.
不要敷衍我
Don't say that name.
你是不会伤害你自己的
You are not going to kill yourself.
你是我的病人 我是你的教士
You remind me of Rabbi Lichtenstein,
我是来救你的 听着
who-who back in Stellring- listen-would argue
我所做的并非严格按照上帝的旨意 但是
that our debasement was not God's doing but Satan's.
听着 但是我会考虑你所犯下的罪行
Listen.
但是我会考虑
But I would argue that the crimes of Klein
你所犯下的罪行
are the crimes of Hitler,
法律定义上的罪行
but the crimes of Hitler are the crimes of the Lord.
算了 亚当
No, no, no, no, Adam.
你去休息吧
You get some rest.
我们以后再说这个吧
We can do this later.
等等
But wait, wait, Wolfie.
这是什么 歌声 285房间 像狗一样叫
The-the thing in 285 barks like a dog,
像狗一样臭 看见这牙印没
smells like a dog, but uh, the teeth?
我会明白吗
Do I know, Adam?
只是个在地下室长大的
It's-it's just some crazy kid raised in a basement
脖子上栓铁链的疯小孩
with a chain around its neck.
小孩
A kid?
他们说这很危险
Gross says it's dangerous.
没人会靠近它
Nobody goes near it.
这是个新项目
He's Gross' special project.
[咆哮和吠叫]
[growling and barking]
你认为
So you think-
在这个房间里没有第二个人么
you think that you are the only one?
- [吠声]  - 是吧？
- [barks]   - Ja?
好吧
Ja.
我来告诉你
Let me tell you,
有其他人
oh, there are others.
感觉到我的存在了么
Me, for instance.
很好
Ja.
哦 好吧
Oh, ja.
我是一个
I am the con man.
伟大的魔术师
I am the freak.
喜欢魔幻
I am the monstrosity.
是天才
I am the genius.
但是真正的天才总是有代价的
But true genius, it comes with a price.
看着吧 这些复杂的绳结
Ja, the singer joins the opera.
是宇宙中最神奇的秘密
The mathematician unlocks the secrets of the universe.
可是我？
But me?
用我的天分
Oh, my gifts, worthless.
没用的 在马戏团里
And so I was marked for the circus.
我离你有一段距离
I was destined for the sideshow.
还有狗窝
And for the doghouse.
[吠声]
[barks]
好吧
Ja.
我怎么知道这个的呢
Oh, you didn't know this, did you?
哦 是的
Oh, ja.
整整一年 我都住在狗屋
For one whole year, I ate from the dog bowl,
乖乖听话些
lived on all fours,
睡在圈里 贴近地面
slept in the pen, shat on the ground.
我成长为一代宗师
I learned from the master.
冲锋队
Sturmfuehrer Rex.
[咆哮和吠叫]
[growls and barks]
但现在你看见 当我的天分驱使着我
But now do you see where my gifts have delivered me?
等一下 来这里
Now, hang on, come here.
等等 等等
Wait, wait, come here.
嘘
Shh.
等等 等等
Hang on. Hang on.
让我看看这个
Ja, let me just see this.
这是狗 这不是一条狗 这是个孩子 这不是个孩子
The dog that is not the dog, the child that is not the child.
这就是他们的看起来的样子 就像他们回到集中营中一样
This is the way they looked, back there in the camps,
他们受着从精神到肉体的折磨
sunken cheeks, tubercular chests,
我掉进了一个无底的黑洞
and from inside the blackened sockets,
那些渴望温暖的眼神 但是生命呢
those eyes sick with fear but alive.
[吹小号]
[playing trumpet]
够了 Arthur
Enough, Arthur.
[液体滴注]
[liquid trickling]
亚当
Adam.
你真丢脸
Shame on you.
这是对幸存者的祷告吗
This is a place for survivors, right?
是的
Yes.
他们在这里受了太多苦了
Well, what is this boy doing here?
这是什么
Why-what are you doing with this comb?
不要这样
Gina, do not-don't make- don't do it with the comb.
好吧 Gross医生把他收进来的
Well, Dr. Gross brought him.
Gross医生
Yes, Gross.
这就是他怎样让自己
He was howling and biting himself,
进入这个领域的
sodden with his own filth.
我们曾经试图从电台得到它
We tried to get that awful chain off him,
但是 你看 它还在
but, you saw; it's still on.
没人比我有更多的
No one has the right to be more than me,
你也没有
not you, not the dog.
- 更多的什么  - 疯狂
- More what?   - Crazy.
一个疯子
He's crazier than me.
你没有疯
You're not crazy.
是的 我很疯狂
I am crazy.
- 不 你病了  - 是我疯了
- You're sick.   - No, I am crazy.
你病了
You're sick.
那只狗在我面前出现 你明白这代表什么吗
That dog is superior to me, do you understand this?
不是吗？
No?
他成功了 我对他产生恐惧
He has succeeded where I have failed.
他是个大明星
He is Gross' star.
我想我有权说
I think I have a right to say-
说你爱我
That you love me.
你怎么知道我要这么说
How did you know what I was going to say?
因为我可以读出你的心思
Because I can read you.
你喜欢疯狂的，衰老的，亚当・斯坦
You love the crazy, the aging, the sub-human Adam Stein.
这是什么
Why is this?
为什么？
Why?
我想我快死了 我是话说多了吧
A healthy Adam Stein, for you, not so attractive.
你知道的
It's important that you know, really know.
这没有区别 但是我自己这么做了
Makes no difference why, but I do with all my heart.
我对我家的人一向很好
Yes, you're a whore, and I use you.
我可以让他们为我准备黄油
Now, listen, my landlady, Ruthchen, the quiet type,
我想
fucking her was like fucking butter.
这轻而易举
Fucking you is like fucking the motorcycle.
你没人性 亲爱的
You're cruel, darling.
这就是开开玩笑么
Oh, Gina, Gina, it's a little humor.
一切
Child, this is what saves everything.
都很顺利
Klein knew it well.
你可以选一天等着
You can weed out more sub-humans in a day
那天我们都可以幽默一把
with humor and Zyklon B
而且我不是一个人
than you can with Zyklon B alone.
这是组合
It's the combination.
是吧
Ja.
亚当
Adam.
你在那儿干什么呢
What are you doing in there?
[笑]
[laughs]
亚当 你从来没有
Adam, you devil.
可怜的孩子 总之
Well, it is Purim, after all,
我可以有另一只刷牙了
and I can get another toothbrush.
现在 开始工作了
Now, back to work.
基本完成了
We're almost done.
我还是觉得它看起来有点太... 我不知道
I still think he looks a little too-I don't know-
健康了
healthy.
你不这样认为吗
Don't you think?
看看这眼睛
Blacken the eye sockets, for your Purim costume.
看看
Rex, hold still.
还有这个
And?
好的 没问题
Oh ja, of course, ja, ja.
来吧 雷克斯
Here we go, Rex.
你是个囚犯
Ja, you're a prisoner.
你吓倒它了 看上去和犯人一样
Look scared; he is the Kommandant.
很好
Wonderful.
应被记下的一幕
A Purim to remember.
司令官 我的家庭
Kommandant, my family.
你知道吗
You're a comfort, Adam...
你拯救了生命
a lifesaver.
在你到来之前 我几乎被逼死
Before you came, it was killing me.
现在好多了
Now it's better.
太好了
Bravo.
太好了 好孩子
Bravo, maestro.
喔！
Whoo!
亚当 亚当
Adam, Adam.
- Schwester  - 亚当
- Schwester.   - Adam?
你今天会看到 所以你要放松
You are looking today so very, very transcendent.
谢谢
Thank you.
不要
Tell me, have you been grooming
这么激动
this little moustachio of yours?
你是个很不错的女人
Oh, this is so becoming on a woman.
披肩也非常好
It's a very, very striking kind of thing of course.
觉得暖和些了么
But do you not think it is a little warm
很好 很好 你可以走了
for the woolen Unterhosen?
谢谢
Thank you.
亚当 亚当你很优秀
Adam, I prayed for you to return,
让我回监狱吧
and you did.
我一定心存感激
That was nice, Schwester, bringing a man back into prison
我怎么会来过这种痛苦的日子
when he's having such a swell time on the outside.
外面很精彩
L'Chaim, Schwester.
嗯
Mmm.
我答应了你的事情 我会做的
I accept your assignment.
现在做你该做的
I will be your holy ventriloquist.
我不得不去看看那条狗
But just now, I have got to see a man about a dog, shalom.
它会离开么
Woe be the shepherds of Israel that feed themselves.
一会儿见
Auf Wiedersehen.
她会合适这个衣服吗
Shouldn't the shepherds feed the flocks?
你可以试试
Good-bye.
我很抱歉刚才就那样跑掉了
I am so sorry that I just popped up before and ran off.
我刚才突然很渴
I got thirsty.
他们虐待你么
Did they torture you?
那个家伙是谁
Who was it?
Colomb吗
Golomb?
那个个子矮的拿着钥匙的
That tiny Torquemada with the jangling keys?
总带着甜酒
Sturmfuehrer Slonim?
你可以告诉我
You can tell me.
你是唯一一个我可以交谈的
You're the only one that I can talk to
你来这里找地方住
in this godforsaken place.
这不是你该做的
Yes, you are not a phony.
对我来说 这是很重要的事情
And to me, this is a- this is a very big deal.
相信我 我可以闻到一公里以外的味道
Believe me, I can sniff one a mile away.
那么你能不能 你能不能记下来
And so can you, can you not?
只有你和亚当・斯坦与这个世界反抗着
It is you and Adam Stein against the world.
你我将会去
You and I, we are going to take the trial run.
你跟我走
On we go.
你就是我的狗
Yes, I know you're a dog.
我了解的
I understand.
没什么丢脸的
There's nothing to be ashamed of.
[吠叫]
[barking]
一边去
Don't panic.
[吠叫]
[barking]
那是脏衣服 很脏的
No, this is laundry, dirty laundry.
乖 我们出去散散步
Ja, let's take a little tour.
哦 看谁来了
Oh, look who's here.
来 跟着我
Look who's coming.
你觉得这对孩子有好处吗
Do you really think this is doing the boy any good?
他是条狗而已
He's a dog, Gina.
他不懂什么叫作尊重
Show a little respect.
来吧
Come on. - Hey.
这是赛狗比赛
Ja, this is Gina Grey's classy ass.
嘘
Shoo.
看谁来了
Ja, looky, look who's here.
从这里看去
Look at them, kid.
这里有很多人
These-these wretched souls have-have chimneys for hearts.
看看 他有迷人的心 Gross希望来自
And Gross tries to heal them with, mescaline, LSD,
墨西哥的消息
hypnotherapy.
知道这是不可能做到的
Knows that it cannot be done.
抓住了吗？
And Seizling?
他说他可以一次扔两块石头
Ja, she thought she could save these walking tombstones too.
我可以救他们
Thought I could save them.
但我从来没有说过我能做到
But I never said that I could.
我对结果从来不作出承诺
I never promised them the burning bush.
离我远点 Arthur
Go away, Arthur.
别惹事 走开
Go light a fire.
会开得怎样了
How's the knitting, by the way?
你别太把自己当回事了
You're not the rebel you think you are.
你知道么
You know what?
看那里
Look over there.
那个站在后面的人
There's a man behind the curtain,
他们才是
pulling your strings.
你知道吗 我明天有个演讲
Ja, I'm giving another talk tomorrow.
表演的历史 狗是现实的人
A history of drama from the dawn of man till the present
它现在就是这样了
entitled "Whisky and Dramaturgie."
一定要来
Do try to come.
好了 所有人都到齐了
All right, are we all here?
是 都到了
Yes, we are.
开始吧
Then let's-let's begin.
嗯
Mm.
[吠声]
[barks]
狗会叫
A dog barks.
但是一只在舞台上叫的狗就不是这回事了
But a dog barking on a stage is no longer a dog.
这个瓶子举例 我倒酒
This bottle, for instance, I pour.
我把它端到嘴边 我喝下去
I raise this glass to my mouth, and I swallow.
嗯
Mm.
我真的把它喝了吗
But am I really drinking,
不一定 请你们
or am I a man playing a man who is drinking?
闭上眼睛
Close your eyes.
这就对了
Yeah, that's right.
Not so fast, Arthur.
Arthur
你先登记去
You've got to register first, please.
名字
Name.
你应该知道吧
Schwester, you know my name.
你还是得说 Arthur 我登记呢
Arthur, we all registered.
名字
Name?
Arthur
Arthur.
姓什么
Last name.
Fine
Fine.
Arthur Fine
Arthur Fine.
写Fine就可以了
Perfectly fine, Arthur.
刚才说哪儿了?
Schwester, where was I?
说到‘我真把它喝了吗’
"But am I really drinking, or am"-
我真要喝了 在表演中
Exactly, folks.
眼睛要直视前方
We're all actors...
喝了以后怎么样呢
in a drama which both playwright
从很久以前起
and director have long ago abandoned.
女士们先生们
Nonetheless, meine sehr verehrten Damen und Herren,
把杯子放下是不行的
ladies and gentlemen, to bring the curtain down is impossible.
表演必须进行
The show must go on.
这是在干什么
Hey, what's going on?
他醉了
He's drunk.
他真的在那里喝酒!
He's really drinking up there.
亚当 你撒谎
Adam, you're a liar.
Fine 安静
Nonsense.
胡说
Nonsense, Arthur.
那是纯水
It is water.
我要教大家的
You, of all people, should appreciate
是表演的艺术
what I'm trying to teach these people, the artifice,
为了生存我们都需要必要的谎言
the necessary lie that we all needed to survive.
嗯
Mm-hmm.
有个很好的例子
Here, here, here's a quick example.
好的
Ja.
1945年
It is 1945.
晚上
It is dark.
人们为了庆祝奔走着
A man is running through the Naliboki Forest
喝着鸡尾酒
with a cocktail?
喝了不少
A Molotov cocktail, ja.
这个人 当然不是所有人都知道
The war is over, but not everyone knows it yet.
Arthur Fine 以前到过集中营
Arthur Fine has been in the camps,
逃跑了
escaped,
在地下偷偷生活
lived underground, with the Bielski Partisans.
[笑]
[laughing]
就是这样
Yes, laughter.
对我们来说 回到故事来
For us, back there, no other way.
你来到了巴勒斯坦
But then you came to Palestine,
那是个晦涩的剧院
this theater of the absurd.
你忘了表演中最重要的规则
And for a while, you forgot the first rule of Dramaturgie.
你找到了你的妻子和女儿
You found a wife, a daughter.
都在
But it seems you were merely observing
受着煎熬
the second law of Dramaturgie, the pause,
他们在游戏中放火
because soon the fires burned again.
你和朋友狂笑着
Laughter sprang forth.
点燃了自己的房子
You laughed as you set fire to your house.
不
No.
你的妻子 你的小女儿
Your wife, your little girl.
- 不 先生  - 都很安全
- Bastard.   - To yourself.
当她们再次在燃烧的火中出现
Then one day, Mrs. Seizling showed up at the burn ward.
你手心里的号码 还在那里
Fortunately, the Dachau number on your arm was preserved,
她认出你了 作为她的一个游客
and she recognized you as one of her flock.
你
You.
不能这样
Curtain.
这个演示的目的是
Now, the point of this demonstration?
就是伤痛创造眼泪 所以大笑者创造胜利
Just as sadness creates tears, so laughter creates the joy.
所以留下的可以造成严重的后果
Don't look so horrified,
我们可以开始
meine sehr verehrten Damen und Herren,
大笑了
to laugh, ja.
如果我的生命中没有笑声
If I had not been able to laugh back there,
我就会死了
I would be dead.
你 我 我们都一样
Me, you, all of us.
285房间
And in room 285,
是个年轻的却什么也不懂的孩子
there sits a young mutt who is laughing at us all.
他怎么看
What does he think,
他比我们其他人都好？
he is better than the rest of us?
我给了他一些校正
I will later give him some corrections.
张嘴
Open your mouths.
大些
Wide.
再大些
Wider.
肌肉放松
Relax the neck muscles.
把鼻子皱起来
Wrinkle the noses.
深呼吸
Take a deep breath.
呼气
Perfect.
啊
Ah.
大家可以大笑了
And laugh.
哈哈
Ha, ha.
大点儿声
Louder.
给个人
Everyone.
都大声点儿笑
Louder, louder.
你们在干什么
What are you doing?
- 都大声点儿笑  - 你们在干什么
- Louder, louder.   - What are you doing?
每个人都是
Everyone.
不能这样
I know that it hurts, ja.
不许笑
No.
看我
Look at me.
我马上就要死了  - 不许笑
I am burning.   - No.
但我依然大笑
I am dying, but I can laugh.
停下 停下
No, stop it!
不许笑
Stop laughing!
他可以出去了
He's like a dog.
他必须停止他所做的一切
He's telling us what to do.
冷静点
He licked his boot.
[吹小号]
[playing trumpet]
[笑声]
[laughter]
[吠叫]
[barking]
你想让我干什么
What do you want from me?
过来这里
All right, come here.
[呜咽]
[whimpering]
把这个狗链子取了
Let's get this dog collar off of you.
[吠叫]
[barking]
[呜咽]
[whimpering]
[吠叫]
[barking]
他不停的流血 必须先给他止血
Intestinal bleeding, swollen limbs.
必须先给他止血
Acute renal failure, I knew it.
我知道 我知道
I knew it.
[狗叫]
[dogs barking]
快点 快点
[演奏忧郁的小提琴音乐]
[playing melancholy violin music]
亚当
Adam!
格蕾琴
Gretchen.
- 爸爸  - 哦 我的孩子
- Papa.   - Oh, my dearest one.
亚当
Adam.
我们可以离开这里么
Try to find her. Ruthie.
亚当
Adam.
求你了 爸爸
Please, Papa.
我爱你
I love you.
亚当
Adam.
拉琴
Play!
再敢看停就杀了你
These people need some Marschmusik.
拉琴
Play!
[疯狂的小提琴音乐]
[frantic violin music]
别有下次
[speaks German]
[电子蜂鸣声]
[electronic beeping]
[悬疑音乐]
[suspenseful music]
[持续的嗡嗡声]
[steady drone]
[疯狂的小提琴音乐]
[frantic violin music]
[怪异的音乐]
[eerie music]
[呼啸]
[howling]
那他妈的到底是什么
What the hell is that?
[呼啸]
[howling]
[喘息]
[gasps]
闭嘴
Shut up.
你别这样 好吗
He's not dead, okay?
[打字机咔嚓声]
[typewriter clacking]
在1942年
It was Purim 1942.
人们都互相拜访
The SS were going door-to-door, clearing out the ghetto.
我的孩子 我可爱的Naomi
My Naomi, my beautiful little Naomi,
她那年可美了
she was Queen Esther that year.
她穿洋装戴皇冠
I'd sewn her a dress and made a crown from a tin can.
我们出去散了步
That night after services, we snuck out.
走了几个街区
The Nazis were a few blocks away,
有时候我知道我在那里
so I knew we had some time.
只是 在外面遇见了Masha小姐
Just outside of the ghetto, there lived a Mrs. Marshack.
她常把孩子们的衣服拿到外面
She used to bring me all her children's coats to mend.
房子里有地下室
And in her house, there was a basement.
地下室下面还有地下室
And under the basement, there was another basement,
那是个陷阱
a pit with a trapdoor.
那时 我的 我的小公主
Down that pit went my-my little queen.
我们就把她扔在那里了 我能听见她的抽泣
As we left her there, I could hear her whispering,
这是为什么 爸爸
"Why, Daddy?"
[打字机咔嚓声]
[typewriter clacking]
她在那下面13个月 亚当
13 months she was down there, Adam.
她还是个孩子
She was a child.
还在发育
Her body had to grow,
那是一片阴霾
and this crown,
她永远走不出的阴霾
she never took off this damned crown.
我还要爱上帝吗
That heartless, blind, mute son of a bitch.
为什么
Why?
来啊 你这不公的老天
Come on, you tyrant!
为什么 告诉我为什么
Why?
Wolfowitz
Wolfowitz.
- 告诉我为什么  - 这就够了
- Tell me why?   - That's enough.
你会伤害到别人的
You're gonna hurt someone.
没事了 都过去了
Tarshish.
那是个关键
This is the point.
带我回去休息吧
Take me inside.
让他留在这里
Let him let out some steam, please.
让他发泄
Let him-let him do it.
为什么 上帝啊？
Why, God?
为什么
Why?
我想那个动物了 那个孩子
He misses you, Adam, the kid.
我从不认为你会伤害它
You know, he didn't really think you were going to hurt him.
你们曾经告诉过我
He told you that, did he?
它最好是不要接近我
Well, you tell him for me that he is better off without me.
它刚才看着你就快死了
He was watching you type just now.
这不可能
Tarshish, this is crap.
不 亚当
No, Adam.
离我远点
Get away from me, please.
等等 亚当
Wait, Adam.
我很累 让我单独留下
Tarshish, I am tired. Leave me alone.
他叫什么
What in God's name?
别告诉任何人好吗
Don't tell anyone, okay?
天知道
I'm counting on you.
别发疯
No crazy stuff. - Right.
等等
Wait, wait.
你看看你 孩子
Do not give me this look, kid.
我生病了
I was sick.
又虚弱
I was dying.
这是在开玩笑么 怎么让你解脱呢
Kidney leaking with the white ashes.
我们会很投缘的 孩子
Oh, we're no good for each other, kid.
现在还不用开始工作
Oh, this is not going to work.
你在干什么呢
What do you want, my Olivetti?
你可以成为专业人士
What, you saw me writing Wolfie's eulogy,
像我一样
now you want to write mine?
做吧 做吧 在这个纸上
That's, you know, that's very intuit-intuitive.
等等 等等
But let's not do it.
我把它放平
Do it on the paper.
等等
Wait a minute.
你会卡住它的
You're going to jam it.
给 我把它放在地板上
Here, I'll put it on the floor.
试试吧
Try that out.
真不错 孩子
Well, damn it, kid.
我内心深处
You're the little maestro.
有这样的声音
Why the hell didn't you say so?
OK
Okay.
我看到了这未完成的
I can see that you're the sentient being,
未完成的什么
and sentient beings need what?
名字
The name.
或许我们
Here, maybe something that you're typing
能看出点什么
can give us an idea.
给 让我看看
Here, let me see.
（读纸上字）
Ah, "fdg fdga."
好吧 这有点古怪
Ja, that has a mysterious ring to it.
那么一些更加简单的怎么样
But how about something with a little symbolism?
你知道你叫什么么
You know who you remind me of?
David
David.
David王
David Rex.
犹太人的王
Ja, king of the Jews,
事实是 简单点的容易被高尚的人
descendant of Adam, forebearer of the Messiah,
原谅
fornicator,
学为死囚奏乐
bloodthirsty warrior,
他们被选出来
built Jerusalem,
在上帝的监督下
brought in God in this...
装入盒子
box.
对吧
Ja.
对 David 狗中之王
Long live Davey, king of dogs.
哦 有趣的一天
Purim, our day of joy.
呸
Bah.
看看 亚当
Look at that, Adam.
他们给我们吃这些
They want us to dress up in costumes.
用省下来的钱来粉饰这里
He saved us from Haman only to toss us to Hitler.
上帝的逻辑不仅是没有逻辑性 而是迷糊不清
God's logic is not our logic, Mr. Wolfowitz,
和上位者较真 突破权威
nor can we begin to fathom His ways.
两千年以来一直如此面对面 即使是我们也不例外
2,000 years we've stood face-to-face, Him and us.
人们仍在试图回避
Then he turned and sicced Rex on us.
嗯 你如果多次苦于面子问题的话就会深信
Still, you're a believer, Mr. Wolfowitz,
你也是 亚当
and Adam too.
你们有的其实是
And your tirades, gentlemen,
长满脓疮的面子
are nothing but manifestos of faith.
Shwester深谙此道啊
Schwester, this is very clever.
我说过吗？- 当然
Did I say this? - Of course.
哈哈 我把它都写下来了
I write it all down.
哦 很快 亚当
Oy, soon, Adam-
[用外语喊叫]
[shouts in foreign language]
嗯Shwester
Schwester, give him a- throw him some scraps.
哦 那是什么
Ah, evolution is hard work.
他很好 很干净 革命道路还很艰巨
Oh, the little embryo is evolving
他接到了 哈哈
a million years at a time.
来吧 我们有事做了
Come on, we have got some work to do.
你写些什么亚当
Writing, Adam? What is he writing?
诗 你可以去打些诗
Poetry, poetry, Wolfie, sheer unadulterated poetry.
到那边去
Blumers, Mrs. Lipowitz.
在我的亚当马戏团停一停 看看这神迹
Stop by my-Adam's circus
来看我的魔术表演
and see the miraculous offspring of Olivetti und Rex.
Heel
Heel.
Heel 快点 我们走
Heel, come on, let's go.
亚当
Adam.
不不不 你不能这样
No, no, no, heel, heel.
过来过来
Come on. Come on.
David
David.
等我
Wait, Adam, me first.
我们说到了Masha的地下室
We were in Mrs. Marshack's basement.
她在那下面呆了有十三个月 亚当
13 months she was down there, Adam.
那究竟是多长时间
How much is that in numbers?
13个月有
13 months is, um-
等一下 共有390天9360个小时561600分
Well, it's 390 days, 9,360 hours.
561600分钟 她被困在那里
561,600 minutes she sat there...
等等
waiting.
上帝 这是为什么
Why, God?
为什么
Why?
我还有个问题
"May his question soon be answered.
不会很困扰 你继续打字
Signed, Abe Wolfowitz."
当你说这‘可能么’之时
Then you say Kaddish, Adam,
你可能觉得新鲜
and maybe serve some refreshments.
你离开了 对不对
You lived, right?
那才是问题所在
That's what matters.
没错
Ja, ja.
亚当马戏团在这里吗
The circus is here?
当然了
Yes, it sure is, come on.
快请进 来来来
Come on, look how excited Rachel is.
好啊 大家都来了
Come on, ja, oh, everyone's come.
谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
谢谢 亲爱的
Thank you, darling.
谢谢
Thank you, Mr. Blum, ja.
Arthur 来吧
Come on, Arthur.
好吧
All right.
谢谢
Thank you.
你可以在门外读
Do the reading outside.
女士们先生们 将会发生什么呢
Ah, ladies and gentlemen, meine Damen und Herren.
这是个好机会
This is your big chance.
准备好了没有
Ready?
我给你们展示的是 狗中之王
I give you the king of dogs, Koenig der Hund,
狗中之王David
David.
[哼唱马戏团音乐]
[humming circus music]
万岁 太棒了
Bravo, bravo.
[鼓掌]
[clapping]
那是David打的
Messages from Davey.
给你
For you.
什么
What?
什么呀
AT&T 300点N\
"AT&T up 300 points."
太棒了 亚当
Bravo, Adam.
[讲外语]
[speaking foreign language]
太好了 他用舌头说话了
He's speaking in tongues.
干得好 亚当 干得好
When, Adam, when?
什么呀
What?
那么 很惊人
He's been pounding out gibberish.
你已治疗那男孩两个月
Nathan, we've been treating that boy for two months now,
教他用自己的方式防卫
making our way through his defenses,
让他和亚当长时间在一起好么
and along comes Adam Stein with a typewriter,
别下定论 那要视情况而定
and you're beaming at me like you've invented penicillin.
我会很高兴
Well, I'm sure Adam will be more than delighted
分享这一进步
to share the credit.
哦 拜托
Nathan, please.
亚当太不稳定了
Adam is unstable.
他太危险了
He's dangerous.
我们对待他的方式 不合情理
Instead of restricting him, increasing his medication,
你给他无限制的特权
you give him unlimited access to the Institute.
你无视他酗酒
You turn a blind eye to his alcohol,
你不管他与护士的调情
his love affair with your head nurse.
读一读
Read.
读就读
What do you mean, read?
不会有坏处
Leave Adam to me.
（读纸上字）
"Gina Grey's classy ass."
你知道么
You know what?
为什么我们不干脆让患者都互相治疗
Why don't we just let the patients cure each other,
这样我们也有时间玩牌了
and you and I can sit around in our pajamas playing cards?
那是你从不相信的奇迹
That is the most sensible thing you've ever said.
哦 来吧
Oh, fine, fine, fine.
狗王
That is my boy, David.
这是我的狗王
This is my king of dogs.
不不不 别这么吃
Do not eat the- do not eat the paper.
啊哦
Ow.
停下来
Stop this.
你不是只狗
You are not a dog.
知道我为什么回来吗
Do you know why I came back?
我无法接受 孩子
I could have died, kid, ja.
我的心在流血
The heart was blocked.
击打着我的胸膛 呼唤着我的名字
Slonim was pounding my chest, calling my name.
我无法阻止它
There was nothing else he could do.
我在愤怒中死亡
And I was wrestling with the Angel of Death.
医生把你交给我
I stopped him at the gate.
知道为什么吗
Do you know why?
为什么
Huh?
我要再见你
[whispering] To see you again.
这就是原因
That is why.
我爱你 孩子
I love you, child.
但别告诉上帝
But it's no damn good.
这爱远比对他的多
You lean on me, we will both go tumbling down together.
[发动机转速]
[engine revving]
[狗叫]
[dogs barking]
[狗呜咽]
[dog whimpering]
17号
Zyklot 17.
我想就是这一天
Rex would have preferred it that way, don't you think?
当俄国人到这里 德军像狗样被杀
When the Russians arrive, they will shoot him like a dog.
起来
Get up.
给你看点东西
I have something to show you.
埃文 甘道夫
Baron Von Hamdung.
你认识么
Do you know the name?
我在集中营听过他
Iron industry, shipping, petroleum.
在战争爆发后不久
Not long after the war broke out,
他由于国籍被捕并送入集中营
he was accused of treason.
一个聪明的会计
His entire estate,
我给他机会 很可笑
Swiss bank accounts, holdings, were nationalized.
局面在崩溃
A clever SS accountant-
这枪里有
well, I thought I was clever at the time-
一枚子弹
was put in charge.
试试吧 你不该错过
He was meticulous,
它躺在那里
which is how he rose so fast through the ranks.
当然是说丹尼尔
But this one file, he put aside.
事实上 是他偷的
In fact, he stole it.
我们在做垂死挣扎 一天又一天
And incredibly, it was never missed.
[狗呜咽]
[dog whimpers]
这没什么 该回去了
Patton's Third Army has crossed the Danube.
俄军占领柏林了
The Russians are in Berlin.
战争结束了
It's the end.
这档已经没用了
For me, this document is useless.
但是 当你面对死亡的那一天
But we had a deal, you and I.
你会选偷生还是反抗
A life for a life.
算了
So here.
拿着这个回去吧
It's Von Hamdung's last will,
那里还有你的地方
the rights to his home and possessions,
你是最得利的
and you are the sole beneficiary.
你曾是条好狗
You've been a good dog.
事实的真相是 我本能拯救你的家庭
The truth is, I could have saved your family,
他们被送入集中营
but it would have been inconvenient.
是我本可以做点什么
I would have had some explaining to do.
开枪
Do it.
[狗呜咽]
[dog whimpers]
[枪声]
[gunshot]
所以你选的是活下去 亚当
So there's life in the old clown yet, eh, Adam?
[1950's初 柏林]
没错 我懂了
Ja, ja, I get it.
亚当・斯坦在家吗
Adam Stein is at home?
（德语）
Herr, Hermann Lichtenstein.
Abe 欢迎
Rabbi.
你看上去不错
Welcome to Valhalla.
亚当
Adam.
看看
Look at us.
怎么会这样
How can it be?
[沉闷的爆炸声]
[muffled explosion]
哦 Rabbi
Oh, Rabbi.
有些问题
It is-it's only dynamite.
我不会做其他举动
They're putting up an apartment block next door.
但你已经先发现了 你怎么发现的
But on my land, no resurrection will occur.
你听到了冯・汉姆顿的话
You have the word of Von Hamdung.
你是怎么找到我的？
How did you find me?
让我说德国人怎么样
The only Jew in Germany should be hard to find?
问问报纸和你自己
You're in the papers, Adam, the newsreels.
让我来问你
Let me ask you.
你的那个大女儿 Ruth
Your daughter, the older one, Ruthie,
你是否厌倦了去寻找她
did you ever try to locate her?
你有了她的消息对吗
Such a cheerful presence, Rabbi.
真的 你照亮了整个房间
Truly, you light up the room.
很遗憾亚当
I'm sorry, Adam.
但你不得不接受
But I have to.
她死了
She's dead.
我们都死了
We both are.
你不得不
What is the point?
如果有必要 你知道吗？
But if you have to, what, know?
不 对
Ja, I did.
我找了四年
For four years, I looked.
我寻找 她没有理由离开我
I put Von Hamdung's blood money to good use, believe me.
相信我
Then it dawned on me, Rabbi.
如果她还活着
If she was alive,
她不会来找我
then it was she who was not looking for me.
亚当
Adam.
她今年已经二十五岁了
She would be 25 this year.
她不会听到她有名的爸爸
She would have heard about the antics of her famous father
一个差不多狗一样的人 一个什么都不是的人
who was once a dog and is now not much of anything.
他本可以救她
And who in the world could blame her
但他选择沉默
if she chose to be silent?
你也是劫后余生
We survived.
你没有罪
It's not a crime.
唯一的罪是这样来谴责自己
A crime is to blame yourself instead of them.
听我说
Now, listen to me.
她还活着
She is alive.
战后
She was in a holding camp after the war.
她嫁给了个意大利人
She married an Italian,
去年他们搬到了以色列
and last year, they moved to Israel.
管家
Heinz.
现在在Haifa岛
She lives as a Christian in Haifa.
三周前我发现了这一点
We were notified three weeks ago
联系了医院
when she was admitted to the Franciscan Hospital.
他们看了报纸并且联系了我们
They looked at her papers and contacted us.
医院？
Hospital?
纳粹 他们虽然摧残了她的肉体和灵魂
The Nazis, they injured her, body and soul,
但她挺过来了
but she lived.
现在 感谢上帝
And now, thank God,
你就要做祖父了
you are about to become a grandfather.
我认为是时候去和她谈谈了
I think it's time to talk to her.
她可能不会原谅 但会听进去的
And if not to be forgiven, then maybe at least to be heard.
我要想想这些 你可以走了
Rabbi, you have some nerve coming here to my sarcophagus.
管家 送客
Heinz, get my gun.
这是她现在的名字 亚当 你自己选择吧
Her name and address, should you so choose.
亚当 你不需要这样惩罚自己
You don't have to punish yourself, Adam.
你为什么在柏林
Why stay in Berlin?
是什么让你待着这里
What's keeping you here?
亚当 你还没死呢
You're not dead yet, Adam.
这里真热
It's so hot in here.
怎么这么热
Why is it so hot?
这个房间很热
It's a hothouse, Adam.
真像个沙漠
Hothouse in the desert, typical.
不管别的 那个女孩呢
What is he growing anyway?
瓜果 土豆 草药都在厨房
Oh, melons, tomatoes, herbs for the kitchen.
嘿
Hey.
今天你在找窗帘吗
Today you were thinking about Gretchen.
不不
Oh, no, no.
女士 没必要这样
Lady, this is not so nice.
你没有权利老是想着格雷琴
You have no right to be brooding about Gretchen.
你可以回答问题 直接面对我
That woman had faith in me.
你要是不正视我
Adam clowning around as she took her final steps,
我不会理睬你
and she had faith in me.
你对任何人都没有信心
You have faith in no one.
我注视着你
I have faith in you.
你在撒谎
You are lying.
住手 请别这样
Don't, please.
除了你没人能得到这样的青睐
No one's been able to get through to him but you,
可怜的孩子
the poor child.
别转化话题
It is not a child.
什么孩子
Do not call him the child.
- 狗 狗  - 打字者
- Dog, he's a dog.   - He types on a typewriter.
他不再犬吠了 我能给你人类仅有的
He doesn't bark anymore.
上帝 那个曾经不是人的孩子
You, God, made him into a child.
现在也是了
He was non-human; now he is human.
等等
Wait a minute.
你在嫉妒吗
Are you jealous?
为什么你说我是在嫉妒
Why can't I be jealous?
我当然嫉妒了
Of course I'm jealous.
我嫉妒那个男孩
I'm jealous of the boy.
我嫉妒这转变
I'm jealous of Gretchen.
我们曾经那么亲密 但是现在
We used to be together so much before.
我可以为你叫
I used to bark for you.
我仍然能学狗叫
I can still bark.
[吠叫]
[barking]
你不是狗
You are not a- you are not a dog.
Gina
Gina.
婊子
Bitch at heart.
别叫了
You-stop barking.
Stop barking.
别这样了 Golomb卡在我们中间
You're not going to come between us.
这个孩子是我的
This child is mine.
两条沙漠中的狗
We are two dogs in the desert.
我去掉了他的面具 现在他想要我的力量
I took off his mask, and now he wants my power.
我不想成为狗
I cannot be the true dog.
他也是
Neither can he.
他是个孩子
He's a child.
需要爱
He needs love.
你最好别插手
You had better not interfere.
[狗叫]
[David barking]
孩子
Keep going, kid.
你需要这样做
We are going to do this.
快走
Marsch, hund.
过来
Come on, hey.
看见那些网了没
You see this fence?
用你的两个手攀着那些网
You are going to grab onto the fence
同时脚站地上
and stand on your feet.
这都是你的错
This is all your fault.
用上我教你的全部
Everything I did for you,
现在 为了我 来吧
and now for me, you are going to do one thing.
站起来 站起来 来吧
Here we go. Stand.
噢
Oh.
起来起来
Ah, hund, hund.
加油
Come on, schnell.
你以为这是马戏团
Okay, you ever been to a circus, huh?
真差劲
Bears, horses, lions,
不准反抗
every goddamn creature on this Earth.
你要用双脚站立
Even Arthur Fine can stand on two feet.
你是男孩
You're not the dog.
不是狗
You're not the boy.
加油加油
Come on, come on, come on.
David
David, David.
做下去 你行的
That's it, darling.
做下去
Do it.
David
David, ja.
亚当 他是个男孩
He's a boy, Adam.
还是个孩子
He's a child.
我警告过你
I told you to leave us alone.
远离我们
I warned you.
你想要的是什么
So what are you?
蜥蜴
Lizard?
水蛭
Leech?
还是小老鼠
The little rat?
好的
Okay.
Yes, okay.
就这样
Ja.
停吧
And stop.
David 做得好
David, get down.
可以了
That is-that's enough.
不不不 让他继续吧
Oh, no, no, no, let him.
他成功了
He's making it.
不要管我
Whore, leave me alone.
David
David.
David 今天够了
David, ja, this is enough for one day.
向下 向下 走
Down, down, down you go.
继续下
Down, please.
我还没做好准备
All right, no more.
我还不能这么做
I am not ready yet.
我不行了
I cannot do it.
我快死了
I'm dying.
请 请
Please, please, please.
请
Please.
闭嘴
Shut up.
看
Look...
看着我
at me.
看
Look.
[咆哮声]
[growling]
快 帮帮我
Come on, help me.
好吧 我抓住他了
Okay, I got him.
咱们走
Let's go.
[亚当吠叫]
[Adam barking]
这次你太过分了 亚当
This time you've gone too far, Adam.
没事了 你没事了
Too far. - It's all right.
你做到了
It's okay; you made it.
你是个汉子
You're a man,
我们的人
our man.
[咆哮声]
[growling]
David
David?
来吧
Come on, kid.
你行的
You can do it.
来吧
Come on.
上帝啊 亚当
My God, Adam.
加油 加油
Come on, come on.
好了
Oh, okay.
[1950年初 以色列Haifa岛]
回欧洲去吧 你这个老家伙
Go back to Europe, you old soap.
你好 我叫亚当・斯坦
My name is Adam Stein.
我来找我的的女儿Ruth
I'm looking for my daughter Ruthie.
乔・格雷奇
Joe Gracci.
哦 约瑟夫
Oh, Joseph.
你好 进来吧
Come in, please.
很高兴见到你
Ja, so nice to meet you.
我打扰你了吗？
Am I interrupting something?
[声音重叠]
[voices overlapping]
[模糊的咕哝声]
[indistinct muttering]
要来杯咖啡吗
Would you like some coffee?
我认为你该离开了
I think you should leave now.
谢谢你的花
Thank you very much for the flowers.
请出去
Outside, please.
请出去吧
Please, outside.
怎么
When?
怎么 她什么时候
When-when did she-
什么时候
When?
她发现了你所做的事
When she found out what you had done.
我们告诉她你死了
That's when she died for the first time.
我不能再让她受伤
And then with every report that came in, she died again.
扮宠物 你在干什么
The Commandant's pet, huh, wasn't it?
当你的妻女
You, what, you played
受迫害之时
while your wife and your daughter
你就在讨好
went to the ovens?
你就这样对Ruth
Huh? And Ruthie?
你知道他们对她做了什么吗
Do you even know what they did to her?
她在哪
Where is she?
不管她在哪里
Wherever she is right now,
我保证她绝对不会
she doesn't want you to be there.
想要见你
I guarantee you that.
我们知道你 亚当・斯坦
We know about you, Adam Stein.
你在纳粹庇护下活着
You lived on Nazi money in a Nazi mansion.
你可以自己找
I can find it.
我自己找
I can find the grave on my own.
你敢吗
Don't you dare.
我带你去
I'll take you.
省省点钱吗
Spare a pfennig?
在那边
It's over there.
当肚子里的孩子还小的时候 他们被埋在了一起
They bury them together when they're that young.
对了 是个男孩
A boy, by the way.
你知道吗 搞笑的是
You know, it's funny, I...
我从来没见过她笑
I never once saw her laugh.
滑稽演员的女儿
A clown's daughter,
却不再笑了
and she could barely break a smile.
那么？
So?
我要说 你是个很会演戏
They say you were quite the performer back there, huh?
那继续演啊
Now, go ahead.
让她笑
Make her smile now.
爸爸 继续啊
Go on, Dad.
为你的女儿 搞笑吧
Do something funny for your little girl.
就这样我来到了沙漠中的研究所
And so I found a home in the desert.
丽贝卡在她的研究所迎接我
Rebecca Seizling herself greeted me at her Institute.
她看着我的眼睛
And she looked me in the eye
真是伟大的杰作
and knew that she had met her prized puppy.
但对她很讽刺
But the joke was on her.
我活着 她却死了
I lived; she died.
[全部用外语演唱]
[all singing in foreign language]
[欢快的音乐]
[upbeat music]
一个已经不是狗的男孩
A boy who is not a dog after all.
[掌声]
[applause]
[失真的音频]
[distorted audio]
[咆哮声]
[growling]
省省点钱吗
Spare a pfennig?
是的
Oh, ma-ha, ja, ha.
Ruth 不要害怕
Ruthie, do not be frightened.
我漂亮的小助手
Ah, my beautiful wife, Gretchen.
够了！
Genug!
普瑞姆？
Purim?
我们在庆祝什么
You're celebrating?
我们为何娱乐
Oh, Purim, on account of that one poor son of a bitch Haman?
谁在流泪
What about the eight trillion tears?
谁该补偿
Who is going to pay for those?
我们的牙齿
The eight trillion teeth and soap suds?
肌肤骨骼
Skin and bones?
甚至毛发都在大声呼喊
The unfertilized sperm, the unborn children,
那些不成文的书 不回报的爱
the unwritten books, the unrequited loves,
没睡觉的床
the unslept-in beds, huh?
你是派遣冲锋队的上帝
You're the God who sends out Stormtroopers,
让他们的脑细胞倍增 让他们比我们聪明
multiplies their brain cells, makes them smarter than us?
我会告诉你我们在庆祝什么
No, I will show you show you what we're celebrating.
你是谁
Schwester, who are you?
Rachel Schwester.
Rachel Shwester
不 举起你的手
No, hold up your arm.
告诉我你的号码
What does it say?
Six, one, three, four, five.
你是谁
Then who are you?
我是61345
I'm six, one, three, four, five.
是的
Yes.
你呢
Blum, you?
Two, four, two, two, five.
是的 我们是谁
Yes, who are we, ja?
其他人
The rest of you, roll up the sleeve.
举起我们的手
Raise those arms.
让我看看你在做什么
Zelda, she knew what she was doing all these years.
我们一起微笑 大家一起
Smile, all of you.
这并不疼
It does not hurt.
曾经很疼 但是过去了
It did; it does not anymore.
手臂伸直
Arms straight up.
我们是 没错 我们是骑士 我们是一支军队 举起你们的手
We are this very night an army of arms.
大声喊出你们的号码
Shout out your numbers.
让他们知道 我们还没有死
Let him know that we are not dead.
61345号
Sieben, sechs, drei, vier, fuenf.
61345 喊出来 喊出来
[voices overlapping]
Six, one, three, four, five.
Seven, one, three, oh, two.
71302 71302
Eight, four, two, nine, six.
Seven, one, three, oh-
7130...
[声音重叠]
[voices overlapping]
Seven, one, three, oh, two!
出来吧
Show yourself.
[声音重叠]
[voices overlapping]
[脚步走近]
[footsteps approaching]
出来吧
Show yourself.
亚当
Adam.
[克莱恩笑]
[Klein laughing]
四肢着地
On all fours, Adam.
那样很搞笑
It's funnier that way.
亚当・斯坦
Adam Stein.
你是德国最搞笑的人
The funniest man in Germany.
你为什么会在这里 Klein
Why are you here, Klein?
你真的认为
Did you really think
你那么容易就摆脱了我的灵魂吗
you could be rid of me so easily?
我一直在这里
I have been here all along.
我是你的一半
I am part of you.
我是和你一起从柏林来的
Me you brought with you from Berlin.
同舟共济
Me you brought with you on the boat.
我随你而来
Me you carried into the desert in your suitcase.
亚当
Adam.
你在寻找什么 亚当
What are you looking for, Adam?
一直在找
Try and find her.
你还是找到了吧 Ruth
Ruthie?
你曾是我的 对吧
You weren't much help to them, were you?
你的妻子和女儿
Your wife and daughters.
我再也不需要你了
I do not need you anymore.
[笑]
[laughs]
你和我
It is only you and me.
是一体的 一样的
We're one and the same.
亚当
Adam.
我还没完成我的事业
We have unfinished business.
该到了审判的时刻
Isn't it time for the curtain to come down?
你犹豫够了么
Hasn't Adam's circus gone on long enough?
现在 做吧
Now do it!
做吧
Do it.
然后你就能摆脱我了
And you'll be rid of me.
这是唯一的方法
It's the only way.
做吧
Do it.
不
Nein.
这不是真的
It is not.
我以为你要离开我
I thought you left me.
我永远在这里
I was here all the time.
你和我
You went away.
我回来了
I'm back.
研究所的生活像以往一样继续着
Rebecca Seizling's Institute continues as before.
对瑞秋・施韦斯特、亚瑟以及其他人来说
For Rachel Schwester, for Arthur, and for the rest,
生活将继续
life goes on.
阿尔伯的梦想实现了
Abe Wolfowitz, his prophecy, however, did come true.
在一个他期待的夜晚
He died in his sleep
在梦中逝去
on the very night that he had predicted.
在研究所里
In the years since I left the Institute,
Gina Grey 再也没有见过探望者
Gina Grey has not come once to Tel Aviv for the visit.
我康复的日子中 亚当对来她说过去了
The moment I recovered, Adam Stein was, for her, buried.
Nathan Gross医生在我的康复中起了很大作用
Dr. Nathan Gross, who had absolute faith in my recovery,
我真的很想念他
him I will miss.
David那年冬天被一个亲戚收养了
David was released that winter into the custody of a relative.
那个亲戚
Gross has assured me that this relative
是个很杰出的人
is the upstanding citizen, the family man,
他能给男孩我所不能给的生活
someone who can give the boy the life that I cannot.
我想他 我的David
I miss him, my Davey.
他写信给我
He writes to me.
告诉我他的进步
I follow his progress,
不久我就会去看他
and I will visit him soon.
他现在有自己的生活
But he has a life now, his own life,
在一个属于他自己的家里成长
and a home in which to grow up.
至于我 我变成了
As for me, I have become...
原来的那个我
the ordinary man.
我回到了Ruth Edelson 民宿
I returned to Ruth Edelson's pension.
我无法让自己
I could no longer give myself diseases
生病或动脑
nor bring about my own end.
我不再关心自己的内心
I no longer carry Klein inside me.
我生活在一个可爱的小城
I live in a lovely valley,
但情绪不再高涨
but the heights are gone forever.
不再抵抗病痛
There are no more frightful deserts,
不再赴汤蹈火
and I no longer leap into the fire.
我怀疑我已燃烧殆尽
I am afraid that I will get burned.
安详平静的生活就是最好的礼物
Sanity is pleasant and calm,
没有真正的快乐亦或悲伤
but there is no greatness, no true joy,
能够时时映刻着内心
nor the awful sorrow that slashes the heart.